<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The abc with the Pater noster Aue, Credo, and .x. co[m]maundementes in Englysshe newly translated and set forth, at the kyngs most gracyouse commaundement</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1545</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08693</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19.6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115785</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851003</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16255</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08693)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16255)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1675:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The abc with the Pater noster Aue, Credo, and .x. co[m]maundementes in Englysshe newly translated and set forth, at the kyngs most gracyouse commaundement</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In the Old bayly by Richard Lant,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Londo[n] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1545]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Estimated publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Consists of 8 pages printed on the outer forme of a halfsheet, with the blank pages of the inner forme pasted together, folded as a pamphlet of 4 leaves.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Hornbooks --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="modern_summary_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 36 -->
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Valentine:</speaker>
                     <p>Why how do you know that I am in love?</p>
                  </sp>
                  <sp>
                     <speaker>Speed:</speaker>
                     <p>Marry, by these special marks:—you have learned... to sign like a school-boy that had lost his A B C.</p>
                  </sp>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <head>UNIQUE XVITH CENTURY ENGLISH CHILD'S BOOK</head>
            <p>A. B. C. WITH THE PATER NOSTER, AVE, CREDE AND X COMAUNDEMENTES. Folio, single sheet; folded to make a booklet of 4 leaves, 12mo. 3⅞ by 2¾ inches. Preserved in full morocco box. Printed at London in the Old bayly by Richard Lant. No date, but about 1536.</p>
            <p>A unique child's book which had disappeared from sight for over a century. Variously considered by authorities as having been intended as a Horn Book or as an education book for the very young scholar.</p>
            <p>Last seen by bibliographers at the beginning of the Nineteenth Century, the volume is described as follows by Ames-Herbert-Dibden's Typographical Antiquities, 1816, Vol. III, page 581, item 1779:—</p>
            <p>"The ABC &amp;c. Without date. Octavo. It begins with five differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Alphabets, and Gloria Patri<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then the Pater-noster, &amp;c., grace before meat, and after. Printed only on one side, to be folded as blank pages to be pasted together, and make one leaf of two; or four small leaves of the whole sheet. Licensed by the Company."</p>
            <p>From 1816 on, the volume seems to have disappeared. Pollard, apparently from the above entry, records the fact that the work was printed by Lant (Handlist of Books Printed by English Printers Bibliographical Society) but indicates no copy known.</p>
            <p>Duff, Century of the English Book Trade also had not seen a copy. He records that the Old Bailey address was the first of several addresses at which Lant printed,—hence books without date printed at that address must of necessity ante-date those of established dates printed at other location.</p>
            <p>Though Pollard, in a haphazard fashion, gives Lant's dates as 1542-1563 (op. Cit.), Duff records that "Richard Lant, Printer, in London, was made a freeman of the Stationers on the 6th September, 1537, and paid 44 shillings for the privilege.... When he started printing, he was living in the Old Bailey." Thus proving Pollard in error, and establishing the fact that in 1537, Lant was already a recognized printer of sufficient standing to be admitted to the Stationers Company.</p>
            <p>The volume under consideration bears a manuscript date of 1536, written in an old hand. While this is not conclusive evidence of its actual date, the writer may have had access to evidence now no longer available. Certainly the sheet was printed before 1542 when Lant was sent to the Fleet prison for printing Tolwyn's The Manne of Synne (of which no copy now survives.)</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16255:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 37 -->
The date of 1536, if it is the correct date, would establish this as the earliest known English A. B. C., the earliest known English Horn Book (for it can be considered as such) and the earliest known book printed in England strictly for children!</p>
            <p>Lant, moreover, is the rarest of all English printers; far more rare, for instance, than is Caxton. Of the many books that he printed from 1536 or 1537 until 1563, most have disappeared entirely. Only two of his works are recorded in the British Museum for instance, and there are none at Cambridge.</p>
            <list>
               <head>Of English A. B. C.s, the following are now known.</head>
               <item>1. The present example, printed by Richard Lant. Unique. Not in the Short Title Catalogue.</item>
               <item>2. A.B.C. for children. J. King. No date. Entered at the Stationers 1561/2. S.T.C. No. 18. Unique copy at Queen's College, Oxford.</item>
               <item>3. The B. A. C. (sic) booke in Latyn and in Englysshe. T. Petyt. No date but said to be 15<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8. S.T.C. No. 19. Unique copy at Emmanuel College, Cambridge.</item>
               <item>4. The A. B. C. set forth by the Kynges Majestie. W. Powell. No date, but said to be 1545. S.T.C. No. 20. Unique copy in the British Museum.</item>
               <item>5. The A. B. C.; with the catechisme. for the Company of Stationers, 1633. S.T.C. No. 21. Unique copy was in the Guild Hall Library, London.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The rarity of these little books requires no summing up after the above evidence.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 38 -->
            <p>The a b c with the <hi>Pater noſter Aue / Credo</hi> / and .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundemen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glyſſhe newly tranſlated and ſet forth at the kyng moſt gracyouſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <add>1536</add> ¶ Printed at Londo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the Old bayly vp Richard Lant</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sample_alphabets">
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <p rend="blackletterType">
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> A a b c d e f g h i k l m n o p q r r ſ s t v u w x y z &amp; <gap reason="symbol" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>〈☐〉</desc>
               </gap>ꝰ. Eſt Amen.</p>
            <p rend="blackletterType">A B C D E F G H I K L M N O P Q R S T V W X Y Z.</p>
            <p>A B C D E F G H I K L M N O P Q R S T V X.</p>
            <p rend="roman">
               <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> A a b c d e f g h i k l m n o p q r ſ s t v u w x y z &amp;. eſt Amen.</p>
            <p rend="roman">A B C D E F G H I K L M N O P Q R S T V X.</p>
            <p>In the name of the father &amp; ſon / &amp; the holy ghoſt. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="Pater_Noster">
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 39 -->
            <head>¶ The ſeuen peticyons of the <hi>Pater noſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr father whiche arte in heuyn / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed be thy na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me.</p>
            <p>Thy kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come.</p>
            <p>Thy wyll be done in erth / as it is in heuen.</p>
            <p>Gyue vs this daye our dayly bred.</p>
            <p>And forgyue vs our treſpaſſes as we forgyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that treſpaſſe agaynſt vs.</p>
            <p>And let vs not be led into tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacyon. But delyuer us from euyll.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="Ave_maria">
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->
            <head>The ſalutacyon of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l / called <hi>Aue Maria.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAyle MARI full of grace / the lorde is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the. Bleſſed arte thou <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>onge women. And bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the fruyte of thy wombe.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="creed">
            <head>The Crede / or the .xii. arty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of the chriſten fayth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Beleue in GOD the father almighty make<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> heuen and erth.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d in Ieſu Chriſt / his only
<pb facs="tcp:16255:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 40 -->ſonne our lorde. Which was conceyued by the holy gooſt / borne of the vyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyne Mary.</p>
            <p>Suffred vnder Pons Pyla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te was crucifyed / deed / bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed / and deſcended into hell.</p>
            <p>And the thyrde daye he roſe a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne frome deth.</p>
            <p>He aſcended in to heuen / and ſytteh on the ryght hand of god the father almyghty.</p>
            <p>From thence he ſhall come to iudge the quicke and the deed</p>
            <p>I beleue in the holy gooſt.</p>
            <p>The holy Catholyke church.</p>
            <p>The communion of ſayntes / 
<pb facs="tcp:16255:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->the forgyueneſſe of ſynnes. </p>
            <p>The reſurreccyon of the body</p>
            <p>And the lyfe euerlaſtyng</p>
            <closer>Amen</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="ten_commandments">
            <head>The .x. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes of allmyghty God.</head>
            <p>THOV ſhalte haue non other Goddes but me</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any graue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ymage nor any lykeneſſe of any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge that is in heauen aboue / or in erth beneth / nor in the water vnder the erth / thou ſhalt not bow downe to them / nor wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhyp them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:16255:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 41 -->
Thou ſhalt not take the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of thy lorde god in vayne.</p>
            <p>Remembre that thou keepe holy thy Saboth day.</p>
            <p>Honor thy father &amp; thy moder</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt do no murther.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not commytte adultry.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalt not ſteale.</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalte beare no falſe wytnes agaynſt thy neybour</p>
            <p>Thou ſhalte not deſyre thy neybours houſe / thou ſhalte not deſyre thy neybours wyfe nor his ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / nor his mayd nor his oxe nor his aſſe / nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is thy neybors.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
            <head>¶ Grace afore meate.</head>
            <l>The lorde aboue / grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs to take.</l>
            <l>His gracyouſe gyftes / with thankes geuyng</l>
            <l>And his goſpell not to forſake</l>
            <l>which is our helth &amp; life laſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</l>
            <p>Our father. &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <head>¶ Grace after meate.</head>
            <l>Thankes to that lords that all hath ſent</l>
            <l>For this our fode conuenient</l>
            <l>And for his worde / which is our helth</l>
            <l>And lyfe of ſoule as ſcripture telth.</l>
            <p>Our father which act in heuen. &amp;c. </p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16255:7"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 42 -->
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
